WHEN they were gone, Elizabeth, as if intending to exasperate herself as much as possible against Mr.
Darcy, chose for her employment the examination of all the letters which Jane had written to her since her being in Kent. They contained no actual complaint, nor was there any revival of
past occurrences, or any communication of present suffering. But in all, and in almost every line
of each, there was a want of that cheerfulness which had been used to characterize her style,
and which, proceeding from the serenity of a mind at ease with itself, and kindly disposed
towards everyone, had been scarcely ever clouded. Elizabeth noticed every sentence conveying the
idea of uneasiness, with an attention which it had hardly received on the first perusal. Mr. Darcy’s
shameful boast of what misery he had been able to inflict gave her a keener sense of her sister’s
sufferings. It was some consolation to think that his visit to Rosings was to end on the day after
the next, and a still greater that in less than a fortnight she should herself be with Jane again,
and enabled to contribute to the recovery of her spirits, by all that affection could do. She could not think of Darcy’s leaving Kent without remembering that his cousin was to go
with him; but Colonel Fitzwilliam had made it clear that he had no intentions at all,
and, agreeable as he was, she did not mean to be unhappy about him.
While settling this point, she was suddenly roused by the sound of the door-bell;
and her spirits were a little fluttered by the idea of its being Colonel Fitzwilliam himself,
who had once before called late in the evening, and might now come to inquire particularly after
her. But this idea was soon banished, and her spirits were very differently affected,
when, to her utter amazement, she saw Mr. Darcy walk into the room. In a hurried
manner he immediately began an inquiry after her health, imputing his visit to a wish of hearing
that she were better. She answered him with cold civility. He sat down for a few moments, and then
getting up walked about the room. Elizabeth was surprised, but said not a word. After a
silence of several minutes, he came towards her in an agitated manner, and thus began:—
“In vain have I struggled. It will not do. My feelings will not be repressed.
You must allow me to tell you how ardently I admire and love you.”
Elizabeth’s astonishment was beyond expression. She stared, coloured, doubted,
and was silent. This he considered sufficient encouragement, and the avowal of all that he felt
and had long felt for her immediately followed. He spoke well; but there were feelings besides
those of the heart to be detailed, and he was not more eloquent on the subject of tenderness
than of pride. His sense of her inferiority, of its being a degradation, of the family
obstacles which judgment had always opposed to inclination, were dwelt on with a warmth which
seemed due to the consequence he was wounding, but was very unlikely to recommend his suit.
In spite of her deeply-rooted dislike, she could not be insensible to the compliment
of such a man’s affection, and though her intentions did not vary for an instant,
she was at first sorry for the pain he was to receive; till roused to resentment by his
subsequent language, she lost all compassion in anger. She tried, however, to compose herself
to answer him with patience, when he should have done. He concluded with representing to her the
strength of that attachment which in spite of all his endeavours he had found impossible to conquer;
and with expressing his hope that it would now be rewarded by her acceptance of his hand. As he said this she could easily see that he had no doubt of a favourable answer. He spoke of
apprehension and anxiety, but his countenance expressed real security. Such a circumstance
could only exasperate farther; and when he ceased the colour rose into her cheeks and she said,—
“In such cases as this, it is, I believe, the established mode to express a sense of obligation for the sentiments avowed, however unequally they may be returned. It is natural
that obligation should be felt, and if I could feel gratitude, I would now thank you. But I
cannot—I have never desired your good opinion, and you have certainly bestowed it most unwillingly.
I am sorry to have occasioned pain to anyone. It has been most unconsciously done, however, and I
hope will be of short duration. The feelings which you tell me have long prevented the acknowledgment
of your regard can have little difficulty in overcoming it after this explanation.”
Mr. Darcy, who was leaning against the mantel-piece with his eyes fixed on her face, seemed to catch her words with no less resentment than surprise. His complexion became pale with
anger, and the disturbance of his mind was visible in every feature. He was struggling for the
appearance of composure, and would not open his lips till he believed himself to have attained it.
The pause was to Elizabeth’s feelings dreadful. At length, in a voice of forced calmness, he said,—
“And this is all the reply which I am to have the honour of expecting! I might, perhaps, wish to be informed why, with so little endeavour at civility, I am thus
rejected. But it is of small importance.” “I might as well inquire,” replied she,
“why, with so evident a design of offending and insulting me, you chose to tell me that
you liked me against your will, against your reason, and even against your character? Was
not this some excuse for incivility, if I was uncivil? But I have other provocations. You know
I have. Had not my own feelings decided against you, had they been indifferent,
or had they even been favourable, do you think that any consideration would tempt me to accept
the man who has been the means of ruining, perhaps for ever, the happiness of a most beloved sister?”
As she pronounced these words, Mr. Darcy changed colour; but the emotion was short,
and he listened without attempting to interrupt her while she continued,— “I have every reason in the world to think ill of you. No motive can excuse the unjust
and ungenerous part you acted there. You dare not, you cannot deny that you have been the principal,
if not the only means of dividing them from each other, of exposing one to the censure of the world
for caprice and instability, the other to its derision for disappointed hopes, and involving
them both in misery of the acutest kind.” She paused, and saw with no slight indignation
that he was listening with an air which proved him wholly unmoved by
any feeling of remorse. He even looked at her with a smile of affected incredulity.
“Can you deny that you have done it?” she repeated.
With assumed tranquillity he then replied, “I have no wish of denying that I did everything in my power to separate my friend from your sister, or that I rejoice in my success. Towards
him I have been kinder than towards myself.” Elizabeth disdained the appearance of noticing
this civil reflection, but its meaning did not escape, nor was it likely to conciliate her.
“But it is not merely this affair,” she continued, “on which my dislike is founded. Long before it had taken place, my opinion of you was decided. Your character was unfolded in the recital which
I received many months ago from Mr. Wickham. On this subject, what can you have to say?
In what imaginary act of friendship can you here defend yourself? or under what misrepresentation
can you here impose upon others?” “You take an eager interest in that
gentleman’s concerns,” said Darcy, in a less tranquil tone, and with a heightened colour.
“Who that knows what his misfortunes have been can help feeling an interest in him?”
“His misfortunes!” repeated Darcy, contemptuously,—“yes,
his misfortunes have been great indeed.” “And of your infliction,” cried Elizabeth,
with energy; “You have reduced him to his present state of poverty—comparative poverty. You have
withheld the advantages which you must know to have been designed for him. You have deprived the
best years of his life of that independence which was no less his due than his desert. You have done
all this! and yet you can treat the mention of his misfortunes with contempt and ridicule.”
“And this,” cried Darcy, as he walked with quick steps across the room, “is your opinion of me!
This is the estimation in which you hold me! I thank you for explaining it so fully. My faults,
according to this calculation, are heavy indeed! But, perhaps,” added he, stopping in his walk, and
turning towards her, “these offences might have been overlooked, had not your pride been hurt by
my honest confession of the scruples that had long prevented my forming any serious design. These
bitter accusations might have been suppressed, had I, with greater policy, concealed my struggles,
and flattered you into the belief of my being impelled by unqualified, unalloyed inclination;
by reason, by reflection, by everything. But disguise of every sort is my abhorrence. Nor
am I ashamed of the feelings I related. They were natural and just. Could you expect me to
rejoice in the inferiority of your connections?—to congratulate myself on the hope of relations whose
condition in life is so decidedly beneath my own?” Elizabeth felt herself growing more angry every
moment; yet she tried to the utmost to speak with composure when she said,—
“You are mistaken, Mr. Darcy, if you suppose that the mode of your
declaration affected me in any other way than as it spared me the concern which I
might have felt in refusing you, had you behaved in a more gentlemanlike manner.”
She saw him start at this; but he said nothing, and she continued,—
“You could not have made me the offer of your hand in any possible way that
would have tempted me to accept it.” Again his astonishment was obvious;
and he looked at her with an expression of mingled incredulity and mortification. She went on,—
“From the very beginning, from the first moment, I may almost say, of my acquaintance with you, your manners impressing me with the fullest belief of your arrogance, your conceit, and your selfish
disdain of the feelings of others, were such as to form that groundwork of disapprobation,
on which succeeding events have built so immovable a dislike; and I had not known you a month before I felt that you were the last man in the world whom I could ever be prevailed on to marry.”
“You have said quite enough, madam. I perfectly comprehend your feelings,
and have now only to be ashamed of what my own have been. Forgive me for having taken up so much of your time, and accept my best wishes for your health and happiness.”
And with these words he hastily left the room, and Elizabeth heard him the next moment open the
front door and quit the house. The tumult of her mind was now painfully great. She knew not how
to support herself, and, from actual weakness, sat down and cried for half an hour. Her astonishment, as she reflected on what had passed, was increased by every review of it. That she should receive an
offer of marriage from Mr. Darcy! that he should have been in love with her for so many months!
so much in love as to wish to marry her in spite of all the objections which had made him prevent
his friend’s marrying her sister, and which must appear at least with equal force in his own case,
was almost incredible! it was gratifying to have inspired unconsciously so strong an affection.
But his pride, his abominable pride, his shameless avowal of what he had done with respect to Jane,
his unpardonable assurance in acknowledging, though he could not justify it, and the unfeeling
manner which he had mentioned Mr. Wickham, his cruelty towards whom he had not attempted to deny,
soon overcame the pity which the consideration of his attachment had for a moment excited.
She continued in very agitating reflections till the sound of Lady Catherine’s carriage made her
feel how unequal she was to encounter Charlotte’s observation, and hurried her away to her room.
CHAPTER XXXV.
ELIZABETH awoke the next morning to the same thoughts and meditations which had at length
closed her eyes. She could not yet recover from the surprise of what had happened: it was
impossible to think of anything else; and, totally indisposed for employment, she resolved soon after
breakfast to indulge herself in air and exercise. She was proceeding directly to her favourite walk,
when the recollection of Mr. Darcy’s sometimes coming there stopped her, and instead of entering
the park, she turned up the lane which led her farther from the turnpike road. The park paling was still the boundary on one side, and she soon passed one of the gates into the ground.
After walking two or three times along that part of the lane, she was tempted, by the pleasantness
of the morning, to stop at the gates and look into the park. The five weeks which she had now
passed in Kent had made a great difference in the country, and every day was adding to
the verdure of the early trees. She was on the point of continuing her walk, when she caught a
glimpse of a gentleman within the sort of grove which edged the park: he was moving that way;
and fearful of its being Mr. Darcy, she was directly retreating. But the person who advanced
was now near enough to see her, and stepping forward with eagerness, pronounced her name. She
had turned away; but on hearing herself called, though in a voice which proved it to be Mr. Darcy, she moved again towards the gate. He had by that time reached it also; and, holding out a letter,
which she instinctively took, said, with a look of haughty composure, “I have been walking in
the grove some time, in the hope of meeting you. Will you do me the honour of reading that letter?”
and then, with a slight bow, turned again into the plantation, and was soon out of sight. With no expectation of pleasure, but with the strongest curiosity, Elizabeth opened the letter,
and to her still increasing wonder, perceived an envelope containing two sheets of letter paper, written quite through, in a very close hand. The envelope itself was likewise full.
Pursuing her way along the lane, she then began it. It was dated from Rosings, at
eight o’clock in the morning, and was as follows:— “Be not alarmed, madam, on receiving this letter,
by the apprehension of its containing any repetition of those sentiments, or renewal of those offers, which were last night so disgusting to you. I write without any intention of paining
you, or humbling myself, by dwelling on wishes, which, for the happiness of both, cannot be too
soon forgotten; and the effort which the formation and the perusal of this letter must occasion,
should have been spared, had not my character required it to be written and read. You must,
therefore, pardon the freedom with which I demand your attention; your feelings, I know, will bestow
it unwillingly, but I demand it of your justice. “Two offences of a very different nature,
and by no means of equal magnitude, you last night laid to my charge. The first mentioned was,
that, regardless of the sentiments of either, I had detached Mr. Bingley from your sister,—and
the other, that I had, in defiance of various claims, in defiance of honour and humanity,
ruined the immediate prosperity and blasted the prospects of Mr. Wickham. Wilfully and wantonly
to have thrown off the companion of my youth, the acknowledged favourite of my father, a young man
who had scarcely any other dependence than on our patronage, and who had been brought up to expect
its exertion, would be a depravity, to which the separation of two young persons whose affection
could be the growth of only a few weeks, could bear no comparison. But from the severity of that
blame which was last night so liberally bestowed, respecting each circumstance, I shall hope to be
in future secured, when the following account of my actions and their motives has been read.
If, in the explanation of them which is due to myself, I am under the necessity of relating
feelings which may be offensive to yours, I can only say that I am sorry. The necessity must be
obeyed, and further apology would be absurd. I had not been long in Hertfordshire before I saw,
in common with others, that Bingley preferred your elder sister to any other young woman in the
country. But it was not till the evening of the dance at Netherfield that I had any apprehension
of his feeling a serious attachment. I had often seen him in love before. At that ball, while I
had the honour of dancing with you, I was first made acquainted, by Sir William Lucas’s accidental
information, that Bingley’s attentions to your sister had given rise to a general expectation
of their marriage. He spoke of it as a certain event, of which the time alone could be undecided.
From that moment I observed my friend’s behaviour attentively; and I could then
perceive that his partiality for Miss Bennet was beyond what I had ever witnessed in him.
Your sister I also watched. Her look and manners were open, cheerful, and engaging as ever,
but without any symptom of peculiar regard; and I remained convinced, from the evening’s scrutiny,
that though she received his attentions with pleasure, she did not invite them
by any participation of sentiment. If you have not been mistaken here, I must have been in an
error. Your superior knowledge of your sister must make the latter probable. If it be so, if
I have been misled by such error to inflict pain on her, your resentment has not been unreasonable.
But I shall not scruple to assert, that the serenity of your sister’s countenance and air was
such as might have given the most acute observer a conviction that, however amiable her temper,
her heart was not likely to be easily touched. That I was desirous of believing her indifferent
is certain; but I will venture to say that my investigations and decisions are not
usually influenced by my hopes or fears. I did not believe her to be indifferent because I wished it;
I believed it on impartial conviction, as truly as I wished it in reason. My objections to the
marriage were not merely those which I last night acknowledged to have required the utmost force of
passion to put aside in my own case; the want of connection could not be so great an evil to my
friend as to me. But there were other causes of repugnance; causes which, though still existing,
and existing to an equal degree in both instances, I had myself endeavoured to forget, because they
were not immediately before me. These causes must be stated, though briefly. The situation of your
mother’s family, though objectionable, was nothing in comparison of that total want of propriety so
frequently, so almost uniformly betrayed by herself, by your three younger sisters, and occasionally even by your father:—pardon me,—it pains me to offend you. But amidst your concern
for the defects of your nearest relations, and your displeasure at this representation of them,
let it give you consolation to consider that to have conducted yourselves so as to avoid any share of the like censure is praise no less generally bestowed on you and your eldest sister than it
is honourable to the sense and disposition of both. I will only say, farther, that from what
passed that evening my opinion of all parties was confirmed, and every inducement heightened, which
could have led me before to preserve my friend from what I esteemed a most unhappy connection.
He left Netherfield for London on the day following, as you, I am certain, remember,
with the design of soon returning. The part which I acted is now to be explained. His sisters’
uneasiness had been equally excited with my own: our coincidence of feeling was soon discovered;
and, alike sensible that no time was to be lost in detaching their brother, we shortly resolved
on joining him directly in London. We accordingly went—and there I readily engaged in the office of
pointing out to my friend the certain evils of such a choice. I described and enforced them
earnestly. But however this remonstrance might have staggered or delayed his determination,
I do not suppose that it would ultimately have prevented the marriage, had it not been seconded
by the assurance, which I hesitated not in giving, of your sister’s indifference. He had before believed her to return his affection with sincere, if not with equal, regard. But Bingley has great
natural modesty, with a stronger dependence on my judgment than on his own. To convince him,
therefore, that he had deceived himself was no very difficult point. To persuade him against
returning into Hertfordshire, when that conviction had been given, was scarcely the work of a moment.
I cannot blame myself for having done thus much. There is but one part of my conduct, in the whole affair, on which I do not reflect with satisfaction; it is that I condescended to adopt
the measures of art so far as to conceal from him your sister’s being in town. I knew it myself,
as it was known to Miss Bingley; but her brother is even yet ignorant of it. That they might have
met without ill consequence is, perhaps, probable; but his regard did not appear to me enough
extinguished for him to see her without some danger. Perhaps this concealment, this disguise,
was beneath me. It is done, however, and it was done for the best. On this subject I have nothing
more to say, no other apology to offer. If I have wounded your sister’s feelings, it was unknowingly
done; and though the motives which governed me may to you very naturally appear insufficient,
I have not yet learnt to condemn them.—With respect to that other, more weighty accusation,
of having injured Mr. Wickham, I can only refute it by laying before you the whole of
his connection with my family. Of what he has particularly accused me I am ignorant; but of
the truth of what I shall relate I can summon more than one witness of undoubted veracity.
Mr. Wickham is the son of a very respectable man, who had for many years the management of
all the Pemberley estates, and whose good conduct in the discharge of his trust naturally inclined
my father to be of service to him; and on George Wickham, who was his godson, his kindness was
therefore liberally bestowed. My father supported him at school, and afterwards at Cambridge;
most important assistance, as his own father, always poor from the extravagance of his wife,
would have been unable to give him a gentleman’s education. My father was not only fond of this young man’s society, whose manners were always engaging, he had also the highest opinion of him,
and hoping the church would be his profession, intended to provide for him in it. As for myself,
it is many, many years since I first began to think of him in a very different manner. The
vicious propensities, the want of principle, which he was careful to guard from the knowledge of his
best friend, could not escape the observation of a young man of nearly the same age with himself, and
who had opportunities of seeing him in unguarded moments, which Mr. Darcy could not have. Here
again I shall give you pain—to what degree you only can tell. But whatever may be the sentiments
which Mr. Wickham has created, a suspicion of their nature shall not prevent me from unfolding
his real character. It adds even another motive. My excellent father died about five years ago;
and his attachment to Mr. Wickham was to the last so steady, that in his will he particularly
recommended it to me to promote his advancement in the best manner that his profession might allow,
and if he took orders, desired that a valuable family living might be his as soon as it became vacant. There was also a legacy of one thousand pounds. His own father did not long survive mine;
and within half a year from these events Mr. Wickham wrote to inform me that, having finally
resolved against taking orders, he hoped I should not think it unreasonable for him to expect some
more immediate pecuniary advantage, in lieu of the preferment, by which he could not be benefited. He
had some intention, he added, of studying the law, and I must be aware that the interest of
one thousand pounds would be a very insufficient support therein. I rather wished than believed
him to be sincere; but, at any rate, was perfectly ready to accede to his proposal. I knew that Mr.
Wickham ought not to be a clergyman. The business was therefore soon settled. He resigned all claim
to assistance in the church, were it possible that he could ever be in a situation to receive it,
and accepted in return three thousand pounds. All connection between us seemed now dissolved. I thought too ill of him to invite him to Pemberley, or admit his society in town.
In town, I believe, he chiefly lived, but his studying the law was a mere pretence;
and being now free from all restraint, his life was a life of idleness and dissipation. For about
three years I heard little of him; but on the decease of the incumbent of the living which had been designed for him, he applied to me again by letter for the presentation. His circumstances,
he assured me, and I had no difficulty in believing it, were exceedingly bad. He had
found the law a most unprofitable study, and was now absolutely resolved on being ordained, if I
would present him to the living in question—of which he trusted there could be little doubt,
as he was well assured that I had no other person to provide for, and I could not have forgotten my
revered father’s intentions. You will hardly blame me for refusing to comply with this entreaty,
or for resisting every repetition of it. His resentment was in proportion to the distress of
his circumstances—and he was doubtless as violent in his abuse of me to others as in his reproaches
to myself. After this period, every appearance of acquaintance was dropped. How he lived,
I know not. But last summer he was again most painfully obtruded on my notice.
I must now mention a circumstance which I would wish to forget myself, and which no obligation
less than the present should induce me to unfold to any human being. Having said thus much,
I feel no doubt of your secrecy. My sister, who is more than ten years my junior, was left to the
guardianship of my mother’s nephew, Colonel Fitzwilliam, and myself. About a year ago,
she was taken from school, and an establishment formed for her in London; and last summer she went with the lady who presided over it to Ramsgate; and thither also went Mr. Wickham, undoubtedly
by design; for there proved to have been a prior acquaintance between him and Mrs. Younge, in whose character we were most unhappily deceived; and by her connivance and aid he so far recommended
himself to Georgiana, whose affectionate heart retained a strong impression of his kindness
to her as a child, that she was persuaded to believe herself in love and to consent to an elopement. She was then but fifteen, which must be her excuse; and after stating her imprudence,
I am happy to add, that I owed the knowledge of it to herself. I joined them unexpectedly a day
or two before the intended elopement; and then Georgiana, unable to support the idea of grieving
and offending a brother whom she almost looked up to as a father, acknowledged the whole to me.
You may imagine what I felt and how I acted. Regard for my sister’s credit and feelings prevented any public exposure; but I wrote to Mr. Wickham, who left the place immediately, and Mrs.
Younge was of course removed from her charge. Mr. Wickham’s chief object was unquestionably my
sister’s fortune, which is thirty thousand pounds; but I cannot help supposing that the hope of
revenging himself on me was a strong inducement. His revenge would have been complete indeed. This,
madam, is a faithful narrative of every event in which we have been concerned together; and if you
do not absolutely reject it as false, you will, I hope, acquit me henceforth of cruelty towards
Mr. Wickham. I know not in what manner, under what form of falsehood, he has imposed on you; but his
success is not perhaps to be wondered at, ignorant as you previously were of everything concerning either. Detection could not be in your power, and suspicion certainly not in your inclination.
You may possibly wonder why all this was not told you last night. But I was not then master
enough of myself to know what could or ought to be revealed. For the truth of everything
here related, I can appeal more particularly to the testimony of Colonel Fitzwilliam, who,
from our near relationship and constant intimacy, and still more as one of the executors of my
father’s will, has been unavoidably acquainted with every particular of these transactions. If
your abhorrence of me should make my assertions valueless, you cannot be prevented by the same
cause from confiding in my cousin; and that there may be the possibility of consulting him, I shall
endeavour to find some opportunity of putting this letter in your hands in the course of the morning.
I will only add, God bless you. “Fitzwilliam Darcy.”
CHAPTER XXXVI.
ELIZABETH, when Mr. Darcy gave her the letter, did not expect it to contain a renewal of his offers,
she had formed no expectation at all of its contents. But such as they were, it may be well supposed how eagerly she went through them, and what a contrariety of emotion they
excited. Her feelings as she read were scarcely to be defined. With amazement did she first
understand that he believed any apology to be in his power; and steadfastly was she persuaded,
that he could have no explanation to give, which a just sense of shame would not conceal. With
a strong prejudice against everything he might say, she began his account of what had happened
at Netherfield. She read with an eagerness which hardly left her power of comprehension; and from impatience of knowing what the next sentence might bring, was incapable of attending
to the sense of the one before her eyes. His belief of her sister’s insensibility she instantly
resolved to be false; and his account of the real, the worst objections to the match, made her too
angry to have any wish of doing him justice. He expressed no regret for what he had done which
satisfied her; his style was not penitent, but haughty. It was all pride and insolence.
But when this subject was succeeded by his account of Mr. Wickham—when she read, with somewhat
clearer attention, a relation of events which, if true, must overthrow every cherished opinion of
his worth, and which bore so alarming an affinity to his own history of himself—her feelings were
yet more acutely painful and more difficult of definition. Astonishment, apprehension,
and even horror, oppressed her. She wished to discredit it entirely, repeatedly exclaiming,
“This must be false! This cannot be! This must be the grossest falsehood!”—and when she had gone
through the whole letter, though scarcely knowing anything of the last page or two,
put it hastily away, protesting that she would not regard it, that she would never look in it again.
In this perturbed state of mind, with thoughts that could rest on nothing, she walked on; but it would not do: in half a minute the letter was unfolded again; and collecting herself as well as
she could, she again began the mortifying perusal of all that related to Wickham, and commanded
herself so far as to examine the meaning of every sentence. The account of his connection with the Pemberley family was exactly what he had related himself; and the kindness of the late Mr. Darcy,
though she had not before known its extent, agreed equally well with his own words.
So far each recital confirmed the other; but when she came to the will, the difference was great. What Wickham had said of the living was fresh in her memory; and as she recalled his very words,
it was impossible not to feel that there was gross duplicity on one side or the other, and,
for a few moments, she flattered herself that her wishes did not err. But when she read and re-read,
with the closest attention, the particulars immediately following of Wickham’s resigning
all pretensions to the living, of his receiving in lieu so considerable a sum
as three thousand pounds, again was she forced to hesitate. She put down the letter,
weighed every circumstance with what she meant to be impartiality—deliberated on the probability of
each statement—but with little success. On both sides it was only assertion. Again she read
on. But every line proved more clearly that the affair, which she had believed it impossible that
any contrivance could so represent as to render Mr. Darcy’s conduct in it less than infamous,
was capable of a turn which must make him entirely blameless throughout the whole.
The extravagance and general profligacy which he scrupled not to lay to Mr. Wickham’s charge
exceedingly shocked her; the more so, as she could bring no proof of its injustice. She had
never heard of him before his entrance into the ——shire militia, in which he had engaged at the
persuasion of the young man, who, on meeting him accidentally in town, had there renewed a slight
acquaintance. Of his former way of life, nothing had been known in Hertfordshire but what he told
himself. As to his real character,
had information been in her power, she had never felt a wish of inquiring. His countenance, voice,
and manner, had established him at once in the possession of every virtue. She tried
to recollect some instance of goodness, some distinguished trait of integrity or benevolence,
that might rescue him from the attacks of Mr. Darcy; or at least, by the predominance of virtue,
atone for those casual errors, under which she would endeavour to class what Mr. Darcy
had described as the idleness and vice of many years’ continuance. But no such recollection
befriended her. She could see him instantly before her, in every charm of air and address, but she could remember no more substantial good than the general approbation of the neighbourhood,
and the regard which his social powers had gained him in the mess. After pausing on this point a
considerable while, she once more continued to read. But, alas! the story which followed, of his
designs on Miss Darcy, received some confirmation from what had passed between Colonel Fitzwilliam
and herself only the morning before; and at last she was referred for the truth of every particular
to Colonel Fitzwilliam himself—from whom she had previously received the information of his near concern in all his cousin’s affairs and whose character she had no reason to question. At
one time she had almost resolved on applying to him, but the idea was checked by the awkwardness
of the application, and at length wholly banished by the conviction that Mr. Darcy would never have
hazarded such a proposal, if he had not been well assured of his cousin’s corroboration.
She perfectly remembered everything that had passed in conversation between Wickham
and herself in their first evening at Mr. Philips’s. Many of his expressions were still
fresh in her memory. She was now struck with the impropriety of such communications to a stranger,
and wondered it had escaped her before. She saw the indelicacy of putting himself forward
as he had done, and the inconsistency of his professions with his conduct. She remembered
that he had boasted of having no fear of seeing Mr. Darcy—that Mr. Darcy might leave the country,
but that he should stand his ground; yet he had avoided the Netherfield ball the
very next week. She remembered, also, that till the Netherfield family had quitted the country, he had told his story to no one but herself; but that after their removal, it had been everywhere
discussed; that he had then no reserves, no scruples in sinking Mr. Darcy’s character,
though he had assured her that respect for the father would always prevent his exposing the son.
How differently did everything now appear in which he was concerned! His attentions to Miss King were
now the consequence of views solely and hatefully mercenary; and the mediocrity of her fortune
proved no longer the moderation of his wishes, but his eagerness to grasp at anything. His behaviour
to herself could now have had no tolerable motive: he had either been deceived with regard to her
fortune, or had been gratifying his vanity by encouraging the preference which she believed
she had most incautiously shown. Every lingering struggle in his favour grew fainter and fainter;
and in further justification of Mr. Darcy, she could not but allow that Mr. Bingley,
when questioned by Jane, had long ago asserted his blamelessness in the affair;—that,
proud and repulsive as were his manners, she had never, in the whole course of their
acquaintance—an acquaintance which had latterly brought them much together, and given her a sort
of intimacy with his ways—seen anything that betrayed him to be unprincipled or
unjust—anything that spoke him of irreligious or immoral habits;—that among his own connections
he was esteemed and valued;—that even Wickham had allowed him merit as a brother, and that
she had often heard him speak so affectionately of his sister as to prove him capable of some
amiable feeling;—that had his actions been what Wickham represented them, so gross a violation of everything right could hardly have been concealed from the world; and that friendship between a
person capable of it and such an amiable man as Mr. Bingley was incomprehensible.
She grew absolutely ashamed of herself. Of neither Darcy nor Wickham could she think,
without feeling that she had been blind, partial, prejudiced, absurd.
“How despicably have I acted!” she cried. “I, who have prided myself on my discernment! I,
who have valued myself on my abilities! who have often disdained the generous candour of my sister, and gratified my vanity in useless or blameless distrust. How humiliating is this discovery! Yet,
how just a humiliation! Had I been in love, I could not have been more wretchedly blind. But
vanity, not love, has been my folly. Pleased with the preference of one,
and offended by the neglect of the other, on the very beginning of our acquaintance,
I have courted prepossession and ignorance, and driven reason away where either were
concerned. Till this moment, I never knew myself.” From herself to Jane, from Jane to Bingley, her
thoughts were in a line which soon brought to her recollection that Mr. Darcy’s explanation there
had appeared very insufficient; and she read it again. Widely different was the effect of a second
perusal. How could she deny that credit to his assertions, in one instance, which she had been
obliged to give in the other? He declared himself to have been totally unsuspicious of her sister’s
attachment; and she could not help remembering what Charlotte’s opinion had always been. Neither
could she deny the justice of his description of Jane. She felt that Jane’s feelings, though
fervent, were little displayed, and that there was a constant complacency in her air and manner,
not often united with great sensibility. When she came to that part of the letter in
which her family were mentioned, in tones of such mortifying, yet merited, reproach, her sense of
shame was severe. The justice of the charge struck her too forcibly for denial; and the circumstances
to which he particularly alluded, as having passed at the Netherfield ball, and as confirming all his first disapprobation, could not have made a stronger impression on his mind than on hers.
The compliment to herself and her sister was not unfelt. It soothed, but it could
not console her for the contempt which had been thus self-attracted by the rest of her family;
and as she considered that Jane’s disappointment had, in fact, been the work of her nearest
relations, and reflected how materially the credit of both must be hurt by such
impropriety of conduct, she felt depressed beyond anything she had ever known before.
After wandering along the lane for two hours, giving way to every variety of thought,
reconsidering events, determining probabilities, and reconciling herself, as well as she could,
to a change so sudden and so important, fatigue, and a recollection of her long absence, made her
at length return home; and she entered the house with the wish of appearing cheerful as usual,
and the resolution of repressing such reflections as must make her unfit for conversation.
She was immediately told, that the two gentlemen from Rosings had each called during her absence;
Mr. Darcy, only for a few minutes, to take leave, but that Colonel Fitzwilliam had been
sitting with them at least an hour, hoping for her return, and almost resolving to walk after
her till she could be found. Elizabeth could but just affect concern in missing him; she really rejoiced at it. Colonel Fitzwilliam was no longer an object. She could think only of her letter.
“His parting obeisance.”
CHAPTER XXXVII.